there are four broad ways to improve
your trading results you can increase
the size of profitable trades decrease
the size of losing trades increase the
percentage of profitable trades compared
to losing trades or increase the number
of Trades that you open once you have a
profitable Traders equation now each of
those can be further broken down into
subcategories but if you really think
about it any Improvement you can make to
your trading either directly or
indirectly impacts one of those four
things so which of those areas have you
worked on can you guess which one is by
far the area that Traders focus on the
least if you said the second one you're
absolutely right reducing the size of
losing trades is the most neglected area
of improvement for most Traders by a
country mile they might focus on
reducing the number of losing trades
which relates to the third area
increasing the percentage of profitable
trades compared to losing trades but
very few Traders think about reducing
the size of their losses as a way to
improve their results in fact it's
usually the opposite in the search for
bigger profits you might look at
widening your stop loss or increasing
your percentage at risk as a result your
losses get bigger as well but ironically
reducing the size of losses is often the
lwh hanging fruit for improving your
results most Traders have a huge amount
of simple inefficiencies in that area
which they've never even considered so
with that in mind let's go through a
simple optimization task that will give
you a quick Improvement in that area but
before I explain it it's really
important that we briefly cover an
important topic first how much should
you risk on each trade do you believe
that all trading opportunities are equal
that they're all the same or do you
think that some opportunities are better
than others I think most people would
agree that each opportunity is different
after all the markets are Dynamic and
each opportunity happens within very
different contexts even even if there
are many similarities there are always
many differences as well therefore
should the amount that we risk on each
trade be the same no that would be
illogical that's why most experienced
Traders will use Dynamic risk the amount
you risk changes depending on the
opportunity now if that's a New Concept
to you you can watch a video up here to
find out more about it so if you are
using Dynamic risk how do you decide
whether to risk more or less on one
opportunity compared to another
have a think about how you're currently
making that decision a really common way
is to base the decision on the size of
the potential profit so risking more
when there's huge potential upside but
that approach is mainly driven by greed
and doesn't consider other important
factors like what if the loss is also
potentially huge what if the
probabilities of the potential outcomes
mean that overall it only has a slightly
positive or even negative expectancy and
if you're not already assessing
opportunities in that that way where you
consider the potential outcomes and
estimate the probabilities and you want
to understand more about how to do that
and why it's important check out the
free trading master class that's linked
Down Below in the description box now a
logical answer to this decision-making
process would be to base your percentage
at risk on either the expectancy of the
trade the probability of a profitable
outcome assuming the expectancy of the
trade is already profitable or a
variation of both so for example if you
base it on EXP expectancy you're risking
more money on the trades that are
expected to generate a higher profit
once the risk and probabilities are
facted into the equation and this is the
basis of the Kelly Criterion which gives
you the optimal position size to
maximize an opportunity however in a
previous video which I'll link up here I
explained why the 2% trading rule is so
effective that's this age old rule that
you shouldn't risk more than 2% on a
single trade and one of the main reasons
for that is is the psychological aspect
of going on a losing streak or
experiencing a steep draw down so with
that in mind if you're basing your
amount of risk on expectancy in some
cases you might be risking more on
trades that have a low probability for
each individual trade but a high
expectancy overall and with those trades
over the long term you'd expect to have
a significant profit but you're likely
to have to endure a long string of
losing trades before you get to that and
in that case when we we think about the
psychological aspect it may in fact be
better to base your percentage at risk
on the probability as long as the
overall trade still has a positive
expectancy but anyway that's a
discussion for another day there are
Arguments for both sides but hopefully
you can see that it's logical to change
your risk percentage for each
opportunity and that it shouldn't be
based on just the potential upside but
also probabilities the potential loss
and so on so either expectancy or
probabilities or a mix of both so
assuming you've been doing that already
or you're planning to start doing it
let's get into that simple optimization
task that you can start doing I call
this a risk calibration and it's really
simple you're going to assess whether
you've been applying the correct
percentage at risk to your trades and
then making any adjustments if you find
that you're not so what you need to do
is create a spreadsheet and you're going
to add all of your trades in order of
the percentage at risk now if you've got
a lot of Trades you can group these
together by increments like .1% at risk
or something like that so here in this
example you can see we're doing it by
every
0.1% now we don't have any trades that
were less than 0.3% so that's the lowest
point and it goes up to the maximum risk
which was 1.8% now those are my personal
risk parameters now if you're not
grouping the trades you'll need to add a
column with some sort of trade ID and
I'd recommend doing it by the asset and
the date so that you can easily find
what each of those trades are if you
want to explore it further you can find
it in your trading journal or however
you're tracking your trades much easier
that way now if you're grouping the
trades you'll need to add a column with
the number of trades in that specific
group because that matters then you need
to add a column for the measure that
you're basing your percentage of risk on
for example if you're basing it on the
probability estimates you'll add a
column and list the probability estimate
that you had at the time of entering the
trades if you're grouping the trades you
can take an average so an average of the
trades in that group it's not perfect to
do it that way but the way I always
think about calibration processes it's
not about getting it perfect it's kind
of like when you think about a remote
control car that's veering to the left
or to the right when you turn it over
you have that calibration to sort of
correct it one way or another and that's
what we're doing here we're just
correcting it correcting it until we get
it closer to being accurate and
basically through this process either
right now or at some point in the future
when you are correctly calibrated you
should find that the measure you're
basing your risk on is correctly aligned
with the percentage at risk so if one's
in ascending order the other should be
in ascending order as well and there are
none that are sort of standing out if
that's the case great you're correctly
calibrated but if it's not the case
there are some steps that you can take
so the first step is to go back through
the trades and adjust the risk
percentages to what they should have
been if you were correctly calibrated so
if you find that one is out of place and
it should have been 0.7% at risk but
actually you did 1% change it to 0.7 and
then look look at when you make all of
these changes how it impacts your
performance if it improves your
performance then you know that you need
to recalibrate and that's going to be a
solution to that but if it negatively
affects your performance so it was
better before you tried to calibrate you
might want to investigate further to see
if there are other areas that need to be
improved and we'll discuss that more in
a moment but if you find that you do
need to recalibrate the next step is to
figure out a simple approach that will
keep you more consistent in how you're
apply the risk percentages for your
opportunities now whenever you're
consistently missing something important
with your trading I recommend using a
checklist to instill the right actions
until it becomes second nature so when
you have a checklist you don't need to
use it forever unless you want to you
just use it until it becomes like
automatic that you don't know how to
think about it you use it to correct
mistakes so in this case you'd figure
out the steps that you need to take to
be more correctly calibrated and add
those to a checklist that you then
follow when you're ENT in a trade on the
other hand it might be that just a few
groups of Trades are incorrectly
calibrated but the rest of it pretty
much is so in that case it might be that
there's something specific about those
particular situations that's throwing
you off it might be just random like you
know it's luck they end up being those
but you should go into your trading
journal and break down those situations
anyway to try and find whether there are
consistent themes or uncertainties that
you're struggling with maybe it's a
particular type of situation or there's
some element in these trades that throws
you off a bit and changes the way you
look at them maybe it was something to
do with how you were feeling that day or
what happened before maybe you already
had five trades and this was the sixth
one of the day and therefore you weren't
really switched on and you know you
lacking mental energy whatever it might
be you might find these consistent
themes so that's why it's always
important to keep trading journals
because it helps you identify these
problems that come from the other data
however if you find that when you change
the data to being as if it was correctly
calibrated it actually has a negative
impact on your performance so your
performance was better when things were
not correctly calibrated compared to
when they were correctly calibrated then
it can mean one of two things either
it's a small sample size and it's just a
bit of variability and it's nothing to
be concerned about or it might be the
case that the problem is not with your
risk calibration okay and I think it's
worth investigating even if we think
it's just a small sample size so if
that's the case for you add another
column to the spreadsheet and in that
column input the actual outcomes related
to The Measure that you're using to
decide your risk percentage so for
example if you're using probabilities
then it means in that column you need to
add the success rate percentages of the
different groups of Trades that you took
there and if those success rate
percentages aren't closely aligned with
your probability estimates it may mean
that it's your probability estimates
that need to be calibrated not your risk
percentages and when you sort out that
part you'll see that everything falls
into place and that probability
calibration is something that will cover
cover in a separate video now of course
this is a simplified approach so that we
could go through it together in this
video and there may be other things that
you have to consider when you're going
through it with your own trading but the
steps that I've outlined are just to get
you started but then you may need to dig
deeper into other areas of your trading
to truly understand what's going on
there but the purpose of this simple
optimization task is to see whether
you're genuinely risking more on the
opportunities that you should be risking
more on and not on the ones that you
shouldn't and just one final important
Point whenever you're working with data
or trying to figure things out with your
trading performance always make sure
that you're starting off with an
appropriate sample size if you only have
a few trades you won't be able to come
to any sort of meaningful or reliable
conclusion so if that's the case your
first step might be to collect a bigger
sample size before you go through this
process and if you want to know more
about the right sample size to use watch
the video there at the top and if you
want to know how to collect more data in
a shorter space of time it's covered in
the detailed guide that's linked to the
bottom thanks for watching